You're listening to TIP. The fact that they compounded at 18% a year for over 40 years now, it's just unbelievable. I mean, it has to be one of the most under the radar long-term success stories that we've ever come across. Right. And to think it all started with acquiring a nearly bankrupt Canadian trucking insurance business with just, you know, $13 million in float and has now grown that to nearly $41 billion. And the bet they put on the housing bubble during the GFC was
Absolutely incredible trade, right? I think they netted over four and a half billion dollars. And so really, the big short should have been about them, not Michael Burry.
This show is not investment advice. It's intended for informational and entertainment purposes only. All opinions expressed by hosts and guests are solely their own, and they may have investments in the securities discussed. Now, for your hosts, Sean O'Malley and Kyle Grieve. Daniel and I researched the gold standard of value investments when we looked at Berkshire Hathaway last year and fittingly, we added it as a position to the intrinsic value portfolio that we run.
So we have some experience looking at insurance based holding companies in Berkshire, Hathaway is one of the best simply because they have the world's best capital allocator leading the business and Warren Buffett and he led it for many, many decades. But I'm excited to look at another insurance business that tends to run much more under the radar than Berkshire simply because its CEO, Prim Wadze, doesn't quite have the same cult like
following his Buffett and lives in Canada too, not the US. So maybe that's a factor. And for a lot of diehard investors though, going to this company's annual shareholder meeting is just as important as going to Berkshires. That's right. And this business is Fairfax Financial and it's compounded its book value at over 18% per year since 1985. Now interestingly, one of the biggest tenants in value investing is at price follows intrinsic value over the long term.
And Fairfax has done just that, compounding its share price at 18% as well. And since 1986, when Fairfax had positive earnings per share, it has compounded its earnings per share at about 15% and just insanely high rate for any business over a 40-year time period. And speaking of Berkshire or Hathaway, they've compounded book value at just a touch under 20% a year since inception. So Fairfax is really not too far behind. And Fairfax is interesting because it really has so many parallels.
to Berkshire from having an incredibly well-aligned CEO who prioritizes shareholders to running a decentralized organization, to taking advantage of float from insurance. There's just a lot of parallels that stand out between the two businesses. Yeah, they really do. You know, Prem Watsa has often been called the Canadian Warren Buffett and I doubt Prem would ever say that himself as he seems to be a very humble person. But I think he's taken a lot of inspiration from Warren Buffett and Berkshire Hathaway.
If you just look up the annual reports, there's a very striking similarity between the two and I don't think that's really a coincidence. But of all the managers I've really analyzed closely, I think I might have a hot take here in some circles, but I'd actually say Prem is a manager that is definitely most similar to Warren Buffett that I think I've ever come across. In business, you seem to see many managers spelt the lessons from Buffett and Munger. But when you dig into what they really do, I think they are more or less just paying lip service to them rather than asking
actually implementing their principles into how they conduct themselves in business and in life. And when you look at Prem Watsa, he aligns just so closely to Buffett and he's been such an exceptional steward of shareholders' capital for over four decades now. We'll be going over many more similarities between Fairfax and Berkshire today, but let's begin here by looking at exactly where Fairfax Financial came from. How did this company come about to even be mentioned in the same breath as Berkshire?
Yeah, so Fairfax began with a very simple idea. So Prem learned that if you run an insurance company, you get access to a float. And the great thing about that float is that you're basically collecting premiums upfront so you can then invest that money for a time before the claims are paid out at a later time. Now, Prem worked very hard to get to Canada from India. And when he arrived, he started working as an investor. And in 1985, he took control of a near bankrupt Canadian trucking insurer owned by Markel. So he renamed it Fairfax.
Now, the reason that he chose Fairfax was simple. He wanted to treat people fairly, hence, fair. The F is for friendly deals. He doesn't take part in any hostile takeovers. And then the AX part is for acquisitions, which is obviously very, very integral to Fairfax's business model. But his blueprint wasn't only based on Warren Buffett. He also studied Henry Singleton of Teledyne to help him better understand how to properly allocate capital. Not just in mergers and acquisitions, but also in the intelligent use of buybacks. When Fairfax was young, his goal was to maintain a 20% ROE.
And the business model, it was quite simple. Just leave the managers alone to run their insurance businesses, then invest the flow. But from my understanding, Fairfax had this interesting chapter in its history that occurred after the great financial crisis. And it was sort of a black mark on an otherwise incredibly successful history. And similar to Michael Burry, Fairfax made a fortune betting against the housing bubble. But that win had some pretty hefty implications for multiple years after the great financial crisis.
Exactly. So what they ended up doing was using these collateralized debt swaps or CDSs on major insurance related businesses like AIG, Swiss Re and Munich Re. Now, this was definitely a macro bet since they had a very good understanding of the assets that were inside of these businesses specific portfolios. So basically what happened, they just didn't like what they saw inside of their portfolios. You know, these CDSs could be seen as Fairfax's own form of insurance in the event that these businesses suffered catastrophic losses. But
The bet didn't work out well at the beginning. It took nearly five years and $500 million for the bet to pay off, which netted Fairfax $4.6 billion during the GFC once it finally hit, which was about four times what Michael Burry made from his great financial crisis bet. That was obviously documented in the movie The Big Short that we just discussed. But the problem, unfortunately, was that Prem kept thinking that there was just another catastrophe right around the corner after the GFC had already happened.
So he kept hedging by shorting the S&P 500 and the Russell 2000. And those hedges unfortunately wiped out nearly all of operating income between 2010 and 2016. And on top of that, book value also slowed to a crawl at just 2% growth per annum. Watsa, however, is luckily very, very open, I think with his shareholders. And he eventually admitted that he made a mistake and he swore off shorting for good. Shorting is tough. It takes an unbelievable amount of skill to do right over a long period of time. You basically have capped upside.
and unlimited downside and i think once you gain a reputation for crying wolf and actually be right then you tend to overweight the likelihood of another crisis and so just recently burry actually closed down his phone and he's made a lot of calls since 2008 that didn't work out nearly as well and in many ways i think we're all.
emotional byproducts of the era that we invest in. And so a lot of people today, including myself, haven't really seen a true financial crisis while investing. So I feel like I almost certainly underestimate the risk of another crisis because it's hard for me to imagine it. And every time the markets have dipped in what the last 16 years, they've pretty promptly rallied back. So I can totally see how when managing billions of dollars and living through something like the great financial crisis, you carry some of these scars that affect
how you invest for a long time afterward. Yeah, I think that's actually completely correct. And if you even look back in time at the difference between Warren Buffett and even Benjamin Graham, Benjamin Graham, you know, part of his entire system was built on the fact that he lived through the Great Depression. So he always thought that another depression was right around the corner. And luckily for Buffett, he was very, very young and I don't think he remembered anything that happened during the Great Depression. So I think you're 100% correct, depending on when you're brought into the market. I think fully, fully affects how you invest into the future.
But I want to look here at exactly what Fairfax does. So Fairfax you can think of is basically a holding company with multiple segments. So they have kind of these three primary segments. The first one is the property and casualty insurance and reinsurance business. So this segment covers their insurance and reinsurance businesses that are all over the world, not just in North America. And when I say around the world, I really mean
You know, all sorts of interesting places. You got Barbados, South Africa, Greece, Kuwait, Hong Kong, Bangkok, Luxembourg, Warsaw, Brazil and Argentina, among many other places as well. Then you have the life insurance and runoff section. And then you have the non insurance business. So this includes restaurants and retail segments and Fairfax India, Thomas Cook India and a bunch of other fully owned private businesses. Now.
I really like the non-insurance part of this business. So I actually own a restaurant franchise or that exited to recipe, which is a restaurant business with about $3.5 billion in system sales. So I followed that segment a little closer than the others. And the other assets in the non-insurance business that I find really interesting are Fairfax India and then Hamlin-Watt's investment council or HWIC. So Fairfax India is actually a TSX listed company. It's kind of like a mini Fairfax. Only its holdings are only in India.
And Fairfax owns about 43% of their business. So that business invests in both public and private businesses as well. And they also invest in debt too. I don't think we've really covered any franchise businesses. So it's not a model I'm super familiar with, but just to comment on Fairfax India, I remember listening to a stock pitch about Fairfax India about a year or two ago, since it does trade separately on the Toronto Stock Exchange.
It was really compelling. It sounds like they own some really unique monopoly type assets like airports or maybe it was like the land around the airports. I don't remember exactly. But I want to discuss the Hamblin-Watt Investment Council a little more. And so it seems kind of like the Buffett Munger setup where they made a lot of the investments together along with other superstar capital allocators like Ted Westler and Todd Combs who were a part of the team at Berkshire.
That's right, Sean. So HWIC is the investing arm of Fairfax, like I mentioned, but really interestingly, Fairfax was actually born out of HWIC and not the other way around. So HWIC today is a wholly owned subsidiary of Fairfax, which basically acts as the investment arm of multiple parts of Fairfax's operations. So they invest funds for the Fairfax holding codes, the property and casualty insurance and reinsurance businesses, the insurance and runoff companies as well as for Fairfax India. So
If you look at Fairfax investments, you can get a pretty good idea that they are deeply, deeply rooted in value investing. The businesses just tend to be quite cheap. So one of their positions, Metlin Energy trades for a P of 0.2X. You heard that correctly, 0.2 times earnings. So when I was looking at it, I actually had to double check to see if it was an error. So they follow traditional value and principles, whether that's the preservation of capital above returns, using a margin of safety, focusing on thorough business analysis.
buying out of favor businesses when they're obviously pretty cheap. And then just holding cash when the market isn't offering opportunities, which is something that a lot of businesses tend to have a hard time doing. I tend to be pretty wary of businesses that have an investment arm because they can sometimes charge pretty exorbitant fees. And there can be actually conflicts of interest that make these relationships not exactly shareholder friendly. But given what you've said so far about PrimWatze,
and how aligned he is with shareholders. I assume he's found a way to make the arrangement work. Yeah, he has, I think. So HWIC does earn fees from the entities whose money that it manages. So in 2025 and 2024, those fees were about $233 million and $186 million. So this business is generating revenue, but the important caveat is that HWIC is fully owned by Fairfax.
So while one subsidiary is paying a fee to the other business, Fairfax, the parent company, is getting the fees at that parent level, which means that no money is really moving. It just kind of nets out. So HWIC is basically just a vehicle for investing money at better returns than its insurance companies could generate by themselves. That's kind of how I look at it. HWIC makes money by earning returns for Fairfax subsidiaries, not by charging these exorbitant fees. The exception to this is in Fairfax, India, where Fairfax does charge them a fee.
The fee is paid in cash or in Fairfax India shares based on a management fee and a performance fee that's tied to a target for increasing the book value of Fairfax India. If it's not already clear, Fairfax is not going to be the simplest business conglomerate for us to break down. But neither is Berkshire. And when you talk about this internal independent asset management arm, it sort of reminds me of capital G at Alphabet. And that's a $7 billion fund that Alphabet runs. And
They've had 16 of their portfolio companies actually IPO, which I think is pretty impressive. They'll definitely recognize a few of them. One of their early investments was actually in Lyft. Yeah. So I think you're completely correct about Fairfax being kind of a difficult business to look at. I mean, it's not a simple business that just has one product or one service that it sells. It has, obviously, it's based around insurance, which is great. But yes, there's a lot of moving parts here. So hopefully I can make it simple for everyone to really understand well.
And so, Hamblin-Watt's investment council is just one of many non-insurance businesses that Fairfax owns. But I think it's worth looking at some more of these assets as the non-insurance businesses have a market value of more than $4 billion. And so, you've spoken about recipe in Fairfax, India. But how are the economics of this segment overall? I mean, are these good businesses to be in? Yeah, you know,
The non-insurance segment definitely makes some money for Fairfax, but it's actually pretty low margin. So in 2025, it reported $397 million in operating profit, which is a nice improvement from $241 million in the prior year. But the segment has margins of just 4.6%, pretty razor thin. The business model for the non-insurance seems to be based on taking these kind of controlling stakes in mispriced assets, then trying to improve them, finance them with non-recourse debt, and then just
Take advantage of being decentralized. Let management do its thing to help increase the value of that business. This can then add book value to Verifax or they can sell partial or full parts of these businesses at a profit or to fund other high returning areas of the business that we'll get into later on today. One of their biggest successes on the non-insurance side was with a business called Digit. And so, Verifax owns 49% of that business and has made an annual return on that of 41.5% a year since 2017, which is
outstanding. And what I like to see is that Fairfax takes a concentrated approach with this position because it makes up over 50% of their investments in India. And so to me, this indicates that Fairfax is very willing to let its winners run. And this is a key principle of how we're trying to run our intrinsic value portfolio. Alphabet, for example, has doubled since we first invested in it. And
Reddit has gone up by a similar amount and we haven't really sold either of those positions because while the stock prices have gone up, they've dramatically increased their intrinsic value. The underlying business has kept up with the stock price. And so as long as we continue to think that they're great businesses to own, well, why would we want to sell and have to try and find equally good businesses to replace them? That's not an easy thing to do. And so it's really tempting to lock in your profits when you've made gains.
But there's one thing we've learned from studying legend investors and covering so many companies on that show. It's not holding onto your winners really can be what differentiates a good investor from a great one. Yeah. And I think that, you know, Prem has probably shown that he is a great investor. And you can obviously see that right here with Digit, which was just a massive winner for them. So Digit is really interesting because it kind of intersects insurance with India and to some degree technology. So Fairfax is invested about
$140 million in that business and its carrying value now is a touch over $2 billion. So, one area I think I should highlight is that Fairfax owns non-insurance businesses in three different ways, which can be confusing. They list their investments as common stocks that are marked to market, common stocks that are equity accounted, and then common stocks that are consolidated. So, just briefly let me try to break this down for you in a simple way.
So the first group is stocks where Fairfax owns just a small piece, just kind of too small to have any real say into what goes on in that business. So their earnings either go up or down along with the stock price plus whatever dividends that they get paid from that business. The second group are larger stakes, so where Fairfax definitely has some influence but it's not a majority shareholder. And the third group consists of companies that Fairfax actually controls and runs their day to day operations.
For these, instead of just taking a slice of the profits, Fairfax actually combines that company's entire financial results with its own. And then it sets aside that portion that belongs to any other owner so it doesn't get mixed with Fairfax's numbers. Let's take a quick break and hear from today's sponsors. Curious about online trading, but haven't taken the first step yet? You're not alone. And Plus 500 futures is a great place to start.
The futures markets are moving fast and with plus 500 you can explore popular assets like oil, gold, S&P 500, Bitcoin and more. From crypto to commodities, there's always something happening. The platform is super easy to use so you can trade on the go right from your phone. You can get started with just $100 and jump into the action. See something interesting? Once your account is open, you can trade it in just a couple of clicks.
And if you're not quite ready yet, you can practice with a free demo account. No risk, no pressure. With 20 years of experience, PLUS500 makes trading more accessible than ever. Check it out at PLUS500.com. Trading and futures involves risks of loss and is not suitable for everyone. Not all applicants will qualify. PLUS500 is trading with a plus. They say every day your business is late to AI. You fall two days behind in the competition.
They're only moving faster. Fortunately, there's NetSuite Next. You probably already know NetSuite, the AI-powered business suite that securely connects all your data, financials, inventory, commerce, HR, and CRM all in one source of truth, trusted by over 43,000 customers. NetSuite Next is the next huge leap because now AI is built into everything you do. It surfaces custom insights throughout your day. AI agents work alongside you on the routine stuff.
And anytime you've got a question about anything, you just ask like you're talking to a colleague. And I use it and really I think you should too. For the first time ever, you can try NetSuite next for free. If your revenue is at least in the seven figures, go to net suite.ai slash tip. Built for every industry, ready for every boardroom net suite.ai slash tip. As investors, we spend all day studying great businesses, but some of the best returns come from building one yourself.
If you've been sitting out a business idea, Shopify makes it easy to actually make it happen. Everything you need to start selling is included and ready from day one. Take the moment your first customer is ready to pay. Shopify checkout helps more of them finish the purchase. And when they come back, their details are already saved. One tap and they're done. And because Shopify handles the setup in the checkout, you get more time to focus on what actually grows the business plus the tools to do it.
If I were starting a business, I would absolutely use Shopify myself. It powers millions of businesses worldwide, from names like Mattel and Gymshark to founders just getting started at Shopify.com slash TIP. With Shopify, nothing stands between your idea and a real business. So go make it one. Start your free trial at Shopify.com slash TIP.
Start your free trial at Shopify.com. All right, back to the show. So this is something that really surprised me when I first began to study accounting as an investor, which is that there are so many different ways to account for the value of a company's investments and the income that those investments produce in GAP accounting. So if it's a publicly traded company and you own a small position in it, then the fluctuations in the stock price of that holding
are treated as losses or gains that impact the income statement. Whereas, if you own a significant minority stake or a majority stake, that completely changes the accounting where you either record your share of the underlying company's earnings as your own earnings or claim all of it and deduct out the minority interest. And so point being, there's a huge difference in recording the changes in stock price of your holding company as income.
even if you haven't sold and locked in any of the gains, and recording a percentage of the underlying company's operating earnings. Those are wildly different things. The idea, to some extent, is to try and reflect the difference in business influence that you're truly a passive owner of and businesses where you can significantly influence the operations because you have so much more voting power or even have majority control of the business.
So now I think we need to discuss the insurance business in more depth here because that segment is really what I consider to be the motor of Fairfax. So the underwriting profits from insurance for 2025 were $1.8 billion of Fairfax's operating profits. So we're about 32%. So it's generating a substantial profit for Fairfax and has risen from 18% in 2021. So I mentioned earlier that Fairfax started out as more of an investment company that utilized the float to grow. But in Fairfax's early years,
The insurance businesses just weren't really that great in terms of the quality. So from 1986 until 2005, Fairfax's average combined ratio actually exceeded 100%. For those unfamiliar with the combined ratio, let me just break it down for you quickly. You can think of it as a report card for how well an insurance company does its job of collecting premiums and paying out claims. And so let's say you collect $1 million from customers for their insurance.
What matters are two things, the money you pay out and claims ultimately, and also the money that you spent running the business, the overhead costs. And if those two things add up to less than $1 million, well, congratulations, you made a profit just from writing insurance. But if they add up to more than $1 million, you lost money on the insurance underwriting part of things.
which you generally try to then make up for with the income you receive from investing the float in the meantime. So you get to hold that million dollars and you get to keep, let's say, any interest that's earned on it. And that is what can make insurance businesses overall be profitable if the actual underwriting isn't. But if you can profitably underwrite insurance and earn income from float, well, those two things combined may for a very, very special business.
And in insurance, this is captured by that combined ratio that we've mentioned. So if the combined ratio is under 100%, the company is making money from writing insurance. But if it's over 100%, that means the company is losing money. So it's really as simple as under 100 good over 100 bad almost. And over the last decade or so, Fairfax is combined ratio about 97%. And so what that technically means is that for, let's say every dollar that they collect is premiums,
they're making $0.03 in profit. So they collected $1 premiums, but they only had to pay out $0.97. Exactly. And I think this really matters because the combined ratio affects the insurance flow, obviously. When an insurance company collects premiums, it holds them until it eventually has to pay it out as insurance claims. But there is a gap in that time. It could be years until it needs to be paid out. In the meantime, that money is generally invested in low returning assets like bonds for most insurance companies.
So the combined ratio tells you what the float costs the company. If it's below 100%, which it has been for Fairfax since 2006, you're essentially getting paid to hold other people's money, which is just a great situation and exactly what Buffett took advantage over his entire career with Berkshire Hathaway. For most other insurance companies, though, the float makes just single-digit returns. A great example is Alled World, an insurance company that Fairfax bought in 2017 for about $5 billion. So the insurance
company had been great with an average combined ratio of 91%, but its float had a track record of just about 4% returns. That's because most insurance companies are run by insurance operators. So investing in low-risk bonds ends up being a pretty simple low-risk process that doesn't require equity specialists to come in and manage the portfolio. And then you can contrast that with the approach that Buffett took as really being a stock investor first.
and taking that float and investing it into wonderful businesses. Exactly. But as we know with Hamlin Watts Investment Council, they clearly have the right people in place to earn very high returns on the float while keeping risk relatively low, which you have to do. So since Fairfax today now aims for an ROE of 15%, we can just see how they'd get that with a business like Allied. So if you can increase the returns on the float,
You don't need to make any incremental returns on the underwriting profits, and you'll actually still earn a really high return on equity on that investment. So according to the great book, The Fairfax Way, Fairfax believed it could earn a 20% ROE on Allied simply by just increasing the float's return from 4% to 7%. Float is like really effectively free leverage. That's what you're describing, especially if you have a profitable combined ratio, meaning that you're underwriting insurance profitably. And so you're enhancing your purchasing power with float
which means that you're buying more assets you'd otherwise be able to and then getting to keep the rewards for doing so. That's free leverage. And you mentioned something there that I think we should chat a little bit more about. And that's how Fairfax's combined ratio has turned from something of liability earlier into being really a major boost for the business today. That's right. So the turnaround really started many years before the numbers I think started showing up. So we have to actually rewind back to 1996.
So Fairfax acquired Scandia America, which was a reinsurance business. They ended up renaming it Odyssey. But when they bought it, it had about $250 million of gross premiums and $290 million of equity. And by 2020, that number swelled to $4.3 billion in premiums and $4.8 billion in equity. So this was arguably the best acquisition that Fairfax had ever made. But during this time, Fairfax had to fix a number of issues with some of its other acquisitions. So TIG, Crum & Forrester,
arrived carrying just these very large reserve deficiencies. They had to spend years fixing how they underwrote insurance just to bring their combined ratios down, which definitely made Fairfax's numbers look kind of uglier until they were able to fix those things. Another lever that they really pressed on was leveraging their decentralized business model and putting the right people in place to lead those insurance businesses. So Prem trusted the managers of the insurance businesses and gave them time to fix things.
Fairfax has presidents who have stayed on literally for decades. They show this in their shareholder letter, which helps insurance companies focus on the long term rather than chasing risky premiums just to boost your short-term performance numbers. If managers of insurance companies are only around for a good or bad cycle, it's actually really hard to evaluate them. You need managers in these businesses to stay for multiple cycles so you can see how good they are at fixing things because repairing these businesses
Won't really show up until years down the road if you're the parent company and you get impatient with your subsidiary Presidents and subsidiary, you know managers you might fire them and later learn that they're actually doing a really good job That's exactly right and I think Buffett talks a lot about this about being a disciplined insurance underwriter and the reason being when insurance is sparse when people aren't willing to go out and
and underwrite properly what you can basically do is you can make business by selling for the wrong price. And unfortunately, what happens in the future is if you do that, well, then you're going to be hit with a number of large claims down the road and that can literally just break an entire insurance business. So I want to move on here a little bit and look at Fairfax's competitive advantages because I think on the face of it, it's not really a business that looks like it has any obvious modes. You know, insurance is most definitely a commodity business and it's also
very competitive. So, when you look at it that way, I mean, insurance doesn't really seem like the type of business that anyone would want to get into. And like I said, you know, if you aren't running an insurance business properly and you're not disciplined, you can literally implode and destroy the entire business. So, besides that though, I would say there still are a number of advantages that Fairfax specifically has, but they're also available to competitors to some degree. I just don't think that they can take advantage of it.
So the first advantage like we've already been talking about here for the last few minutes is the combined ratio, which is trended in the right direction due to very, very effective management. The fact that Prem has access to an ever larger float and can earn higher and higher returns on it than most insurance companies is also just a massive advantage. Just to give you an idea, the float has grown to about $40.8 billion up from $13 million in 1985. The second advantage is the capital allocation track record, which spans over 40 years. So their long-term return on investments is about 7.7%.
And even though that number is trended down somewhat since the early days, I think it's one that they can reasonably maintain for quite a long period of time. If the average insurance company earns a return of let's say 4%, which is closer to the longer term return of bonds, then this is just a very, very big advantage because it means that an insurance company will just earn more money simply by being part of Fairfax rather than remaining as a single entity. I would say though that there are other companies out there that come to mind that probably
do a better job of generating higher returns on float. It's obviously Berkshire Hathaway, but also Markell comes to mind too. And so underwriting insurance profitably, if we haven't said it enough, is just so hard to do. And like you said, it's a commodity business. But then to expect to be able to do excellent investing on top of that is really just almost like an unreasonable thing to ask of most companies. And that's why most companies can't do it well. And that's why it's such a special thing to find companies like Fairfax and Berkshire and Markell, where they have this
formula for writing insurance well and also simultaneously being great investors. That's right. And I think you just brought up the kind of key point there where in order for these businesses to really, really succeed, you need both of those. You need the talented operators of the insurance businesses and you need people who can invest really, really well. And it's very, very important, both of those kind of work in conjunction. And even if you do have really, really good investors, they're still handicapped to some degree because regulators
basically won't allow you to invest 100% of a float, for instance, into just equities. I don't think there's any place that does that. Just different jurisdictions have different regulations, but you have to obviously really, really, really careful with that money because if a whole bunch of claims come in, you have to pay that out and you can't just be gambling on the stock market. You have to be able to have that float available to be paid out. So the last competitive advantage that I want to mention here isn't really a traditional one either.
And that's just the culture that Prem Watts has built inside of Fairfax. Throughout the years, Prem has acquired some incredible operators. Fairfax has an exhaustive list of presidents who have been with their company for multiple decades, both before and after being acquired by Fairfax. I think it's easy to see why. Given Fairfax's decentralized nature, it often buys insurance companies that were already very well run.
All Fairfax requires that they really just keep running them well and then Fairfax takes care of growing their flow. And Fairfax also tends to internally promote their executives. So this is really good for culture because if you are inside of Fairfax and you're just great at what you do, if a promotion becomes available, you know that you're probably going to have a really, really good chance at getting it because Fairfax is unlikely to look for an outsider to fill that position.
The best example of acquiring talent was actually from Odyssey. Fairfax got Andy Barnard and Brian Young. So as of today, Brian Young is the president of the Fairfax Insurance Group, a position that was previously held by Andy Barnard, who then moved to the role of chairman of the group. And they've worked together for 35 years and 25 of them have been under Fairfax. So I probably had my own biases because TIP has sort of a decentralized structure, the company that we work at here. And we also hire
from within. So like I said, I have my biases toward thinking that it's a pretty good model. But yeah, there is a lot of evidence that giving talented people the space and the discretion to just do their jobs well without being micromanaged and without multiple layers of middle management and all these other different forms of bureaucracy that you tend to get better business outcomes. So it is pretty cool to see that Fairfax has a similar structure to that.
That's right. So I like to switch gears here and look at Fairfax's debt situation. So through much of Fairfax's history, they haven't really feared debt and have used it to actually help fund a lot of their M&A. So as of today, they have about $14 billion of debt and this is split among the holding company insurance and reinsurance companies and non-insurance companies. But with cash, their net debt position is about $11.6 billion.
But this cash position doesn't actually include the insurance flow, which is currently valued at $73 billion. So even though the cash available for investments for Fairfax is pretty low, they're actually still in a very, very good financial position. Fairfax has always carried debt to fuel its acquisitions, but when you have an ROE as high as they do, it makes sense to purchase businesses with a little leverage. I'm focused on a few key metrics to evaluate Fairfax's financial health. First is just their interest coverage ratio.
and this is simply operating earnings divided by their interest expense. Right now, that sits at a very comfortable level at about 10x, but it's actually trended a little lower over the years from 14 times in 2023. Now, total debt to capital has ranged from about 26% to 33% and currently sits right in between that number. And I think sticking within that range makes a lot of sense as they can continue to add new businesses, whether that's insurance or non-insurance to their portfolio to help continue driving more and more growth.
Or they can buy out minority shares in the businesses that they already do own once they know that it's a really, really good fit and that the business model has been validated. It does feel like it would be fair to call Fairfax a serial acquirer. And one of the hallmarks of serial acquirers is using debt consistently to finance further acquisition. So where do you see debt going in the future? I mean, is it likely to just simply keep trending upward? Or
Is there a chance that they actually deleverage in the future and increase their equity value relative to the debt holdings? I think that given they've had this kind of debt to capital number that stays in a pretty tight range around 30%, my assumption is that probably is going to stay that way into the future. So as long as they're continuing to generate profits and increase their shareholders' equity and capital base, I assume they'll continue to take on moderate amounts of debt. Now,
The good thing about this for Fairfax is that they can raise debt quite easily and don't have to dilute shareholders in the name of growth. Since 2018, diluted shares outstanding have trended downward from about $28 million to about $23 million. The businesses they bought over the decade have had various pricing tags, some as low as $103 million for Singapore Re. Then you have some larger billion-dollar plus acquisitions such as Allied World Insurance for $4.9 billion and Golf Insurance for $1.4 billion.
You know, they definitely do need access to leverage to buy some of these bigger deals. I can see how Fairfax would definitely need access to more capital to make more acquisitions since the pipeline for doing so does not seem to be slowing down anytime soon. And plus, as you mentioned, they can buy out minority stakes in businesses that they already partially own. And so they've already deployed some capital in these minority buyups, if you want to call it that, at Allied World, Gulf Insurance and BRIT.
and raising their ownership levels in all three effectively by deploying capital to buy more skin in the game with those businesses. And so they actually just closed a $1.65 billion deal for Kennedy Wilson holdings as well, I believe. That's right. And speaking of acquisitions, I actually think this is probably a good time to assess the capital allocation of Fairfax because this is a very, very important part of the thesis. So I think there's just a lot of positives here.
First is the 18.7% compound annual gain in book value per share over 40 years. I think this alone just shows you that they have deployed capital very effectively and have continued to grow profits at a very strong rate. ROE, Return on Equity, is a primary metric that they use here to analyze the capital efficiency. It's a very positive story with ROE at 19% for fiscal year 2025. They have a stated goal of 15% ROE.
If they could do that, which they've been doing for well over 40 years here, I think you'll likely earn returns that track this ROE number. Those are definitely really strong and healthy numbers, especially post-2021 coming out of COVID. And they've maintained a range right around that 15% number, it seems like. But they clearly had some weakness leading up to the pandemic. So can you just explain what was going on there?
Yeah, so ROE actually went negative because of something I mentioned earlier, which was the erroneous thinking that other, you know, GFC type events were right around the corner that Fairfax could benefit from. So these investments into the CDSs were expensive and directly consumed much of Fairfax's operating earnings. Additionally, the market actually did really well during this time. So the opportunity cost of shorting the market was very, very high. So during that time, the book value decreased a couple of years in 2011, 2013 and 2016.
But that wasn't the only reason for the depressed operating metrics. 2011 was a brutal year due to a multitude of catastrophic event like the Japanese earthquakes and tsunami. And this caused their combined ratio to go up significantly up to about 114%. I want to harp on one of the things you mentioned earlier. And that's how much respect Prim Watsa has for both Buffett and Henry Singleton, who's lesser known but still an incredible investor. And so I know Fairfax has done some really interesting things in terms of capital allocation to help increase
shareholder value with Odyssey. That's the insurance business that we've discussed a few times today. Yeah, they did some really, really interesting financial engineering, which I think helps explain just how savvy they are with capital allocation. So with Odyssey, they actually ended up selling off just a 10% stake in the business at one time. So here's the nifty financial engineering though. They sold the 10% stake in Odyssey at a book value of 1.7 times. Now, that number might not mean anything to people who don't follow insurance, but that's actually a pretty high
multiple for an insurance company. And once Prem realized that he could earn the premium by selling off a piece of Odyssey at a high valuation, he just jumped on it. But the real reason he did this was to increase Fairfax financial shareholders' ownership stakes. So the proceeds from this divestiture were used to buy more Fairfax shares, which at the time of the deal were actually trading for only 0.9 times book value. And this is just, you know, capital allocation at its finest. You see something expensive and then you buy something cheap. It sounds really easy, but it's very, very rare to see in reality.
Let's take a quick break and hear from today's sponsors. One part of being an investor that I don't think gets enough attention is how hard it can be to continue to improve as an investment researcher. And for myself, I often find that when I finish a great conversation with some industry expert or fund manager, my head is full of ideas. But by the time I sit down to write it all up, half of them are already gone. That's why I've been using Plod Note Pro.
It's a small device that sticks to the back of my phone and captures the conversation and hands me back a clean, searchable recap. And so the key points, the follow-ups, the things I usually want to act on, it has all of that. And that allows me to stay present in the room and set a scribbling notes that I won't be able to read back later. And I notoriously have very bad handwriting. And so it's changed how I prep and how I follow up with investors. It's also built for people who take conversation seriously. Enterprise grade security.
So if you're recording calls with clients or industry contacts, that's covered too. So if you live in meetings, calls and interviews, we'll give it a look. Go to plod.ai slash WSB and use code WSB for 10% off. That's plod.ai slash WSB code WSB and always get consent before you record a conversation. They say every day your business is late to AI, you fall two days behind and the competition
They're only moving faster. Fortunately, there's NetSuite Next. You probably already know NetSuite, the AI-powered business suite that securely connects all your data, financials, inventory, commerce, HR, and CRM all in one source of truth, trusted by over 43,000 customers. NetSuite Next is the next huge leap because now AI is built into everything you do. It surfaces custom insights throughout your day. AI agents work alongside you on the routine stuff.
And anytime you've got a question about anything, you just ask like you're talking to a colleague and I use it and really I think you should too. For the first time ever, you can try NetSuite next for free. If your revenue is at least in the seven figures, go to net suite.ai slash tip. Built for every industry, ready for every boardroom net suite.ai slash tip.
Curious about online trading, but haven't taken the first step yet? You're not alone. And Plus 500 futures is a great place to start. The futures markets are moving fast and with Plus 500, you can explore popular assets like oil, gold, S&P 500, Bitcoin, and more. From crypto to commodities, there's always something happening. The platform is super easy to use so you can trade on the go right from your phone. You can get started with just $100 and jump into the action.
See something interesting? Once your account is open, you can trade it in just a couple of clicks. And if you're not quite ready yet, you can practice with a free demo account. No risk, no pressure. With 20 years of experience, plus 500 makes trading more accessible than ever. Check it out at plus500.com. Trading and futures involves risks of loss and is not suitable for everyone. Not all applicants will qualify. Plus 500. It's trading with a plus. All right, back to the show.
Well, so that that's the key point there that you mentioned Cal right? It sounds simple, but you just you don't see it happen and it's a nuanced conversation wide But I think one of the reasons you don't see it happen is that when a business is trading cheaply It also just becomes harder for that business to sell pieces of itself at a premium price But since Fairfax in some ways is is really a some of the parts play even if Fairfax as a consolidated kink lomerate
doesn't have the best numbers, it doesn't mean one of its subsidiaries is not just absolutely blowing it out of the park. That's right. And another really interesting strategy Fairfax took to raise even more money for buybacks was their use of these things called total return swaps or TRS. So you can think of a TRS as kind of a derivative, kind of like an option, but with a few differences. And the main one being that you take part in the gains of the upside and you take part in the potential losses if the value of the TRS goes down.
but you don't actually have to own the stock. You just kind of put down a deposit. So what Fairfax did was during COVID-19, they bought these total return swaps in Fairfax's stock. Now, they knew at that time that Fairfax was undervalued having just gone down about 50% in price. And from that time, Fairfax recovered very, very well over the years, netting Fairfax about $2 billion in cash from these total return swaps. And much of that cash was then used to repurchase even more shares of Fairfax.
That's very, very cool. I think that's super interesting the way they approach that. One of the underappreciated aspects of buybacks is the timing of when they're done. Doing buybacks in your stock at an all-time high is actually not the right time to do it, even though a lot of companies do it then, because chances are that your shares are overvalued. And so really, if you're going to be very precise and tactical about your buybacks, you want to do them when pessimism for your business is at an absolute bottom.
You are completely correct, Sean. Fairfax shows a great chart showing just how their share account has meaningfully shrunk over time. And the most meaningful number is just how many shares they bought at prices that are a fraction of today's price of about $2,340. They bought back shares in 2019 at an average price of just $473. In 2020, they bought back shares valued at about $500. I think this just kind of goes to show you that they're very good at buying back shares and understanding Fairfax's value and kind of pulling the trigger when
Fairfax is at a depressed price level. One other thing that caught my eye when looking at Fairfax was they do pay a dividend. Kyle, I know you're not the biggest fan of dividends, nor would I say that I am in most circumstances, especially when that business can deploy capital at high rates of return, meaning that ultimately they would create more value by reinvesting and paying out dividends. But I digress. The upside is that Fairfax's dividend is
you know, a very small percentage of earnings that they pay out and the dividend yield is only, you know, 1%. You know me very well, Sean. So obviously, I'm not crazy about dividends either. Over the past 12 months, though, they paid about $350 million in dividends. And so like you just said, you know, that's money that could have been used to fuel the M&A engine. But, you know, it's also a small enough number that I think I'm okay with it, provided that the yield doesn't continue to rise. And the number of support that the yield is actually continuing to trend down. So
I'm not super concerned here about the dividend. The dividends have actually decreased over the past three years while profits have increased. So the fact that they pay a dividend is definitely not a deal breaker for me when it comes to Fairfax Financial. Dividends can be seen in different ways. For instance, when insiders hold large amounts of shares, dividends actually can be seen as an alternative form of taking a salary. And so if a business has a reasonable dividend and management can take lower compensation correspondingly, that is maybe not necessarily a bad thing.
for all shareholders. Yeah, and that's exactly the case, I would say, with Fairfax. So Prem Watsa had a salary of about $600,000 since the year 2000, and it hasn't changed at all since then. And he also receives no bonuses, no profit participation, nor does he participate in any equity or pension plans. So, you know, I think this is a very reasonable deal for a leader who has compounded his business at high rates for over four decades. But I also think it shows that Prem understands how to create alignment between himself and the shareholders.
So Prem Wassa, through a holding company, as well as his personal ownership, has 43.3% voting rights of Fairfax Financial. Fairfax has been through a period where it was attacked by shorters. So this large voting stake helps kind of the business stay protected from potential short attacks in the future. But Prem's economic stake is somewhere around 10% of the total shares. And with his current holdings, he makes somewhere around $19 million per year in dividends. So I would say that
This is definitely part of the reason that Fairfax pays a dividend as it helps compensate the CEO who you can argue is very, very underpaid relative to how much value he's created at Fairfax. Yeah, I mostly like it. I would say that with one caveat. Prim doesn't have a performance incentive. And I like managers to have a performance incentive aligned with creating shareholder value. And so I think we can assume that the incentive here is sort of implied that with
the majority of Prime's net worth being in Fairfax's shares, he is naturally incentivized to continue increasing Fairfax's value. And since he doesn't hold any options, he takes part in both the upside and more importantly, the downside of any declines in Fairfax's share price, which will of course mirror its intrinsic value over time. But how about the rest of the management team? I assume they have different compensation packages, but maybe we can go over that in some more detail here.
Yeah, so it's probably not a huge surprise, but the remaining executives are making a very reasonable base salary in that $600K to $1.5M per year range. There's nothing obvious to me here that would raise any red flags, but most businesses have red flags and they're short and longer-term incentive plans. So let's look there in a little more detail. So I can already see your eyes rolling here, Sean. As Fairfax does have an options-based award, but this system reminds me a lot of Lyfko's options plan.
in that the options that Fairfax grants are actually non-dilutive of a characteristic that's incredibly rare in most corporations. So Fairfax's equity-based awards are based on subordinate shares that have already actually been issued. So you can kind of think of it as Fairfax buying these shares on the open market, then granting them to their employees. So once they grant, no dilution is actually taking place. And the vesting schedule is quite long, with 50% vesting in five years and the other 50% vesting in 10 years.
Fairfax has no pension plans, so these options serve as its replacement. I think I like the long-term nature of the options along with the non-dilutive effects, but they still are, to some extent, time-based awards. Now, I will commend them for having these expiration dates for executives that go out past 2040. I think that's quite impressive and something that I don't think I've ever seen before. Now, I really do admire it. If more of our portfolio companies took this approach to non-dilutive stock awards where you actually have to
buy real shares using cash rather than just printing shares magically. I think we'd see compensation expenses dramatically reigned in and it would put more of a pinch on cash flows. But I also think boards would be much more careful about the comp packages that they structure and that is really the true benefit. That's right. And so just to briefly go over the other short-term incentive plan, it pays out about double of base salary and its discretionary in nature.
it's made up of both cash and options. And these bonuses consider the performance of the executive in light of Fairfax's guiding principles. So for 2025, they gave about a 250% bonus as they had record results across the entire board. So the circular mentions a couple things. It mentions underwriting profits, interest and dividend income, as well as a high rate of achievement in compounding the book value per share. So my assumptions are that's kind of what they're being paid off of. Now, normally I don't like incentive plans that are really
so vague because I kind of like to be clear about what management needs to do in order to get their bonus. But I think when you look at Fairfax's guiding principles, it's pretty hard to argue that following them to a T won't produce stellar results and won't increase the intrinsic value of the company. They mentioned things like compounding book value at 15% annually, focusing on the long-term over quarterly results being open.
with communications with shareholders and then just having a lot of honesty and integrity. And really just a lot more characteristics that you'd be thrilled to have when you're investing in a business. I'm probably being a stickler, but I always have mixed feelings when you can earn back your entire salary and more just on short-term targets. And on the one hand, I mean, that could mean that the salary is very modest, which would be a good thing for shareholders. Or it could mean that it's just way too easy to get paid off of short-term targets or maybe that
the payout on short-term targets is so generous that it's a distraction from or sort of a detriment to these longer-term targets that matter more for shareholders. But for the most part, I think it's a very good incentive structure overall. And part of the guiding principles is based on risk and minimizing risk as much as possible, which I think is a very intelligent approach, of course, because many companies engineer really effectively their own demise by taking large risks.
to boost short-term results to meet quarterly earnings targets from Wall Street, but actually really positioning business to be more vulnerable longer-term. Yeah, I like the focus on risk mitigation here too. And I think that having it as a guiding principle is very admirable. And since the business has been around for so long, I think it's quite clear that they follow these principles very, very closely. But I think we should get into the real risks to Fairfax because they most definitely exist. So,
I mentioned earlier that insurance isn't really a moaty business. I don't think that's a hot take by any means. And even the non-insurance businesses aren't exactly wide-mote businesses either as they range from mattress stores to restaurants to retail. So let's get started with the largest risk that I see for Fairfax, which is shocks to the investment portfolio. During the year when Fairfax struggled from 2010 to 2016, the reason wasn't that they were underwriting bad insurance. It was actually that their portfolio suffered drastically due to the equity hedges.
But on top of that, if global equity markets were to experience large drawdowns, say in the 10% area, Fairfax estimates a $1 billion decrease in net earnings, a 20% drop would decrease net earnings by nearly $2 billion. This reminds me a bit of a business that you pitched earlier this year in WISE. And I know they've recently taken a hit to their investment income growth. And that was due to global interest rates dropping from effectively 3.9% to call it 3%. So for businesses that are connected to
global equity markets or interest rates and are really tied to those. I mean, this can provide a major boost, but it also can be a significant detractor from future returns. Interest rates give it and they take it. And so I also think if the business is safe though during these times and has the right capital base and liquidity, then it tends to sort of even out to the upside over a long enough time horizon.
since Fairfax does have the cash and liquidity on hand, as well as the ability to generate profits from other areas of the business outside of just income from investments and float, then they should be able to withstand a hit to global markets. And that's the key right there. If you have a long-term time horizon for these businesses, the best time to pick them up is actually when their share prices are weak due to cyclical market exposure. So the thing I like about a business like Fairfax is that the market corrections tend to be quite short-lived.
So if you buy near the bottom, you won't have to wait around for years for the cycle to turn as it usually turns within 12 months and often much quicker. Now, the next risk that I'd focus on here is one that you can probably assume and that's key man risk. So it's very similar to businesses that I've covered recently in SpaceX with Elon Musk or QXO with Brad Jacobs. I think Prem Watsa is a pretty big part of the thesis here with a pretty big caveat. So with QXO and SpaceX,
Those aren't businesses that I think are close to as decentralized as how Prem has made fairfax. This makes me think the better example might be more like Constellation Software and Mark Leonard. I think Constellation would never have made it to where it is today without Leonard, but the decentralized nature of the business that he built also means that the engine is going to keep humming along even after he's gone, which he now is not a big part of the business. And Prem also controls 43% of the votes.
For some businesses, you might run the risk that the CEO steps down to become the chairman and then a new CEO comes in who is really just a figurehead while the chairman now runs the show. So Coca-Cola in the 1980s was like this before the power struggle finished in favor of Roberto Goisetta. But I think that he's done a really, really good job of making it so he's still important. But I think because of how decentralized it is, I think that the business is going to continue to run very, very well even after he's gone.
Prim Watsa is now 75 years old. So if Prim Watsa wants to leave or needs to leave, where would they turn to find a suitable replacement? So the board reviews this annually. So I don't think it's going to really come as much of a surprise for shareholders once the prime decides to step down. Fairfax has said that they already have someone in place that would be more than suitable to take over many of his responsibilities.
Now, there's no definitive answer to who would take over, but given that Fairfax has nearly always promoted from within, it would likely be someone a little younger than Prem, who has been with the business for a long period of time. Peter Clark, who is the company's president and chief operating officer, appears to be at the top of that list. So, as a president, all company officers report directly to him. He's been with Fairfax for nearly 30 years. But even more importantly, he's had roles in Fairfax, such as the vice president,
the chief operating officer, the chief risk officer, the chief actuary, and he's been a member of Fairfax's executive and investment committees. So, you know, he's one of these executives who's adept in both insurance and investing, which I think make him a great choice to lead the business once the prem decides to step down. It's worth noting that Watsa has actually stepped back as a vice chairman of Hamlin-Watsa Investment Council in 2019. So, the investments have actually been running smoothly without participation from Watsa.
It would be great to see Prim leading the company into his 90s like Buffett and Munger, but that's probably not a realistic standard to grade people on. So anyways, now with Fairfax being an insurance company, there must be some risk embedded inside of that. From the research I've done on Berkshire Hathaway, previously, of course, the biggest risk were around the insurance side of things and specifically insurance reserving for losses and catastrophe risk.
How do you see Fairfax having a similar risk with its insurance companies? How do you think about that? Yeah, totally. You know, if you screw up the underwriting part of insurance and end up having to pay a larger amount of claims relative to the premiums that you charged, like I've already mentioned, you can break the business. So you need to have insurance reserves stocked up to pay out any claims from any major catastrophes. And if you're under-reserved, that can spell an insurance company's doom.
So, in the early 2000s due to a couple of insurance acquisitions, they brought in books that were pretty much poorly under-reserved. In 2001, Fairfax actually lost money for the first time due to the losses from the World Trade Center and reserve deficiencies amid a very poor insurance market. But since COVID, Fairfax has done a really good job with its KPI. Prior year development or PYD.
So PYD refers to how an insurance reserves for claims from past accident years change as those claims actually settle over time. So when an insurer writes a policy, it has to estimate and set aside money, which are reserves, for claims that it expects to pay, many of which won't be paid out for many, many years. And those estimates are never exactly right, so the insurer has to revise them in later years. And as a result, you get a redundancy or a deficiency. Now you want a redundancy as this means that the original reserves were more than enough.
And once the claims are settled, you can actually release the reserves which go straight to earnings. In a deficiency, you are under-reserved and the insurer has to add more money to cover the shortfall. This raises the combined ratio and obviously negatively affects profits. But since 2020, Fairfax's PYD has been favorable, adding back hundreds of millions of dollars each year, which helps increase profits and makes sure the company is underwriting properly. Okay. All right. Well,
We've covered a lot of the ground. I think it's that time of the show where we try and talk about the intrinsic value of Fairfax Financial. How did you value this business? Yeah. So Fairfax is a very, very interesting business to me. When I release my episode on a great book covering the business called The Fairfax Way on TIP 783, which I'll link to in the show notes. I often wondered to myself, why exactly I don't own Fairfax? Because I can honestly say, I don't think I've ever written a book that made me want to buy a business more than that book did.
You know, when I think about Fairfax, it checks off pretty much every single box I look for. High capital efficiency, check, high insider ownership, check, aligned incentives, check, long history of creating shareholder value, check, large one way for growth, check. And since I've released that episode, you know, I keep asking myself, why don't I personally own it? And I think the reasons that I give are becoming harder and harder to justify. The one area of the business that I'm not craziest about is the exposure to catastrophes. Well, I think Fairfax is a very well run business.
This is one of the reasons that I tend to stay away from insurance companies. I really find it hard to own businesses that are facing these really, really massive headwinds that are completely out of their control. And if Berkshire didn't have the absolute fortress balance sheet that they have, I would probably feel differently about it. But we have seen how utility liabilities and wildfires have weighed on Berkshire for sure. But I'm not sure that admittedly. I mean, do you think this is a risk that they're able to hedge much by selling to reinsurers or
does the buck really stop with them and they have the most exposure? Yeah, I mean, they do have some of the reinsurance businesses. So they clearly understand that part of the business and can deploy capital in some parts in that way to help reduce risk. But I don't want to digress too much. I want to go over my base case here for Fairfax. So the thing about Fairfax that's interesting is that the business of Fairfax is quite complex, but the actual evaluation, I think, is kind of simple, which is kind of surprising to me. So
Basically, what you do with an insurance business is you tend to use book value to evaluate them. So a natural capital efficiency number that directly impacts book value isn't return on invested capital, but it's actually return on equity. That's why we discussed ROE here today. And then you basically apply a price to book ratio to that terminal value and there's your terminal value and you're good to go. So I assume that Fairfax stays true to its long-term goal of achieving about a 15% return on equity.
And this is a number that provides additional margin of safety given that the five-year average ROE is nearly 21%. I assume that their ability to allocate capital remains top notch and that the insurance and non-insurance businesses continue to turn a profit and are run very, very well, which they seem to be doing here. So, with these assumptions, it gives me two numbers, the book value and the business's net earnings. From there, it's a pretty simple path to calculate the ending book value, which I'm using at the end of 2030.
I get a book value of about $2,424. Then I assume the terminal multiple remains at the same number that it has today at around 1.3 times book. And this is a number somewhere around the midpoint of the last decade's multiple. But that was also a severely dragged down by COVID. So I think the business continues to grow at about a 15% ROE. And this is a pretty reasonable multiple to put on it. So applying that, I get a terminal value including dividends of about $4,600 Canadian, which offers about a 14.7 annual per return.
Just for context for listeners, as you think about Kyle's assumptions here, Berkshire trades at one and a half times book value. So actually, the multiple you're using comparatively is pretty reasonable and cheaper than Berkshire's. Already, I can tell you that if they can achieve that 15% ROE target, I'm pretty confident the stock is attractively priced. But how about we hear the bear case before we make any decisions about wanting to add the business to our portfolio? That's right, Sean. And for the bear case, it's equally quite simple.
I assume that they just have a couple of weaknesses in the returns of their portfolio, which drops their ROE to about 11%. Now, ROE has gotten to this point, historically speaking, leading up to COVID. So it's definitely not out of the realm of possibilities. Perhaps they maybe decided to chase profits in some other segments that drag down profits for a time. Now, with the reduction in ROE, I apply a lower price to book ratio of just one times. And with these assumptions, I get a value including dividends of about $3,000 Canadian. And this is still an annual return of 5.3%. So
I think this shows that this business does have really, really good downside production. Another thing to keep in mind is that this book value means that the business is trading somewhere around liquidation value. You can argue that some of the assets would be marked down further, reducing the liquidation value. But even this is probably wrong. So Fairfax actually holds some of its investments that are not marked to market and they believe are heavily, heavily undervalued. So I think the business is pretty cheap in this scenario and you still will make a positive return.
Point being there. There's a double whammy if returns disappoint the company is also going to be punished with a lower Multiple that's something you want to account for whenever you're modeling a bear case and that's get a crush your returns So I apply a 55% probability to my base case a 25% probability to my bear case and about a 20% probability to my bull case with all that I get a business that's worth about $2,400 at a 20% margin of safety now this is a touch above the current price of $2,300 but
If you'd like to take a closer look at how I arrived at these numbers, please subscribe to the Intrinsic Value portfolio newsletter, which will give you direct links to the model so you can play around with it yourself a little bit and see if you have a different view on the value based on your own assumptions. So, I mean, really, I mentioned that this business is one that I've thought a lot about owning and am I making a mistake in not owning it? Probably, but I think to the point that I made earlier about the insurance cyclicality that kind of scares me off. And then the other thing that kind of
gives me pause is simply just the complexity of the business. I mean, there's just so many different areas of the business that you have to understand. It's one of these businesses where you essentially have to place a lot of trust in Prem Wassa to do what's right. And I mean, that's probably a good place to put trust. I mean, he's been doing this now for four decades, but I just kind of can't get over the hump of the difficulty of kind of understanding all the different moving parts of this business. So for me, I think I'm okay with passing on this business for now.
I will definitely be paying very, very close attention to it though, because based on what's happened with this business and based on what can happen with catastrophes, the profits of the business can get hit pretty hard. And in that sense, if this business were to come down significantly, which it could, if this business came down to say 1500 bucks, I don't know if I could pass up not adding it. But that's just my opinion. Sean, what do you think?
Yeah, you could do a whole lot worse than investing in Fairfax. And if I was in maybe a more conservative stage of my financial life, perhaps closer to retirement, I would probably see Fairfax as a great way to have some equity exposure with probably more limited downside than let's just say the median stock out there on the major stock exchanges. But at the same time, I don't see any reason to get fantastically excited about the return prospects. I mean, with pretty high confidence, I
I can guess they'll be decent, but it's not likely to be a homerun. And that's why we've been trimming our Berkshire position today too, to fund investments in companies like Uber, where we feel much more strongly that the business is severely undervalued and the company has tremendous untapped earnings potential. So boring investing is good investing. But when you have some truly enviable software companies selling at steep discounts to their 52-week highs and objectively
some of the lowest valuations that they've traded at in many years, companies like Adobe, Intuit, Salesforce, and so on. I find that to be more compelling to turn over those rocks and look at them, which is what I've been doing. I sort of feel like Fairfax and Berkshire are always there to fall back on, but they're probably not my first choice at the moment of being the most interesting things to put capital in. Well, folks, that's it for today. But I'd like to leave you with a quote here by Prem Watsa. Our earnings are lumpy.
We have never had guidance in 23 years because we have ups and downs and take a long-term view. In 22 years, we have lost money just twice, but our book value and equity has grown dramatically. Now, it's pretty rare for a CEO to discuss his business with such transparency, but I think that you will find that Prem is basically an open book when it comes to Fairfax. And this is a characteristic we look for in all businesses we want to own for the long term. And with that, I'll see you next time. Thanks for listening to TIP.
Follow the Investors Podcast on your favorite podcast app and visit theinvestorspodcast.com for show notes and educational resources. This podcast is for informational and entertainment purposes only and does not provide financial, investment, tax or legal advice. The content is impersonal and does not consider your objectives, financial situation or needs. Investing involves risk including possible loss of principal and past performance is not a guarantee of future results. Listeners should do their own research and consult a qualified professional before making any financial decisions.
Nothing on this show is a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell any security or other financial product. Hosts, guests, and the Investors' Podcast network may hold positions in securities discussed and may change those positions at any time without notice. References to any third-party products, services, or advertisers do not constitute endorsements, and the Investors' Podcast network is not responsible for any claims made by them. Copyright by the Investors' Podcast network. All rights reserved.